Finding Aid for the Kenneth MacKenna Collection of Material About George Bernard Shaw LSC.0670
UCLA Library Special Collections
Kenneth MacKenna collection of material about George Bernard Shaw
1885-1949
UCLA Library Special Collections
MacKenna, Kenneth
LSC.0670
1.5 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
1 folders
George Bernard Shaw (1856-1950) started his writing career ca. 1876 and went on to become a playwright, wit, and critic. He won the Nobel Prize for literature (1925) for his work which is marked by both idealism and humanity, its stimulating satire often being infused with a singular poetic beauty... He was also known as an advocate of social reform. The collection consists of manuscripts, correspondence, pamphlets, ephemera, and art objects by, or relating to, George Bernard Shaw.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mr. Kenneth MacKenna, 1956 and 1959.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942333473606533
Biography
George Bernard Shaw was born July 26, 1856, in Dublin, Ireland; attended Wesleyan Connexional School; he started his writing career ca. 1876 and went on to become a playwright, wit, and critic; known as an advocate of social reform, he co-founded the Fabian Society (1884); vestryman and borough councilor in London in the late 1880s; Nobel Prize for literature, 1925; among his plays are: Heartbreak house (1920), Man and superman (1905), Back to Methuselah (1922), and Saint Joan (1923); his plays adapted to film include Pygmalion (1938) and Caesar and Cleopatra (1946); books include The intelligent woman's guide to socialism and capitalism (1928) and Everybody's political what's what (1944); he died November 2, 1950.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of manuscripts, correspondence, pamphlets, ephemera, and art objects by or relating to George Bernard Shaw.
Items Removed from Collection
Back to Methuselah. London: Constable & Company. 1922. Copy signed by roster of actors who appeared in the play. At the end of page Only the author by G. Bernard Shaw (greatly pleased with the Envoy). Catalogued in rare book section.
Intelligent woman's guide to socialism and capitalism, London 1928. 5 line inscription to Floryan Sobeniowski, dated 13th July, 1928. Yes: this is a first impression. You can tell by page 442. On the fifth line there is a mistake in grammar: the word were should be was. The first correction made, though not the only one, was of this error. Signed. Catalogued in rare book section.
John Bull's other island. How he lied to her husband. Major Barbara. London 1907. Inscription to Mrs. Emery from G. Bernard Shaw, 13th December 1907. Catalogued in rare book section.
Mrs. Warren's profession. London, Grant Richards. 1902. 2 line inscription to J.H. Levy, doughty champion of Personal Rights, holograph, signed, 5th June 1902. Catalogued in rare book section.
Moore, Edris - dedication to in Dramatic Opinions and Essays. Signature of G.B. Shaw. date August 23, 1917.Catalogued in rare book section.
Press Cuttings: a topical sketch. London. 1909. Inscription Mrs. Emery from yours faithfully, G.Bernard Shaw, November 1909. Catalogued in rare book section.
What I really wrote about the war. New York, Brentano's [1932]. With lengthy inscription to William Randolph Hearst, dated San Simeon, March 28, 1933. My dear W.R. Nobody will ever know what we two really wrote about the war. Think of the articles we wrote.... think of the truths we might have told... Well, we both got into honorable trouble early in the war and kept in it to the end, etc. Catalogued in rare book section.
Dramatists, Irish -- 20th century.; Authors, Irish -- 19th century.; Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950.
- 2. Beethoven Broadcast by Bernard Shaw. (?). Published: Radio Times, March 1927 with slight alterations., Typescript carbon copy with corrections and alterations in Shaw's handwriting in ink. 6pp. (Box 1)
- 3. Caesar and Cleopatra. Prologue (as adapted for the Polish stage) (?)., 1928; Typescript in English and Polish. 5 and 6pp. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  At top of English version holograph note by G.B. Shaw, Prologue written for the Forbes Robertson's farewell performance at Drury Lane and used at Barry Jackson's revival. Adopted to Polish history for the 1928 production by Arnold Szyfmen in Warsaw. Signed. Polish translation signed by Floryan Sobieniowski. Leather slip case.
- 4. Camera Work, no.14., and Camera Work, no.42/43., 1906 1913. (Box 1)
  Contains: G. Bernard Shaw on the London exhibitions, reprinted from the Amateur Photographer, October 1901.
  With dedication from Alfred Stieglitz to G.B. Shaw and penciled corrections in the margin.
- 5. Candida., (1893).; Typescript of play with holograph corrections used during rehearsals of original production. In 3 parts with part of Morel. 4 parts, in slip cover. 27pp., 25pp., 20pp. (incomplete) 10pp. (Box 1)
  General note
  On title page: Janet Achurch Carrington... given to me by G.B.S., March 14, 1893. Mounted on silk, in slipcase.
- Carrington, Janet Achurch
  See: Candida.
- 6. Draft Manifesto submitted to the section by Bernard Shaw. The International Socialist Bureau (British Section), 3rd September 1915.; 11pp. (Box 1)
  At head of title page in print Strictly private and confidential. Title page has 8 line holograph notation by G.B. Shaw.
- 7. Dufferin and Ave, Frederick Temple Hamilton-Temple Blackwood, Marquis of, 1826-1902. Speeches delivered in India. London, 1890. (Box 3)
  Copy from Shaw's library with his signature, dated September 24th, 1890. 2 line note in Shaw's handwriting on title page
  - Emery, (Mrs.) Polloc., 1875-. (Box 3)
    See: John Bull's other Island.
    See: Press Cuttings, London, 1909.
  - Galton, Frank Wallis., 1869-. (Box 3)
    See: Metropolitan Borough Council Election.
- International Socialist Bureau (British section). Draft Manifesto submitted... by Bernard Shaw.
  See: Draft Manifesto.
- 9. [Irish Co-operation]. The muddle over the Irish grant., Holograph manuscript foolscap. 2pp. (Box 2)
  Together with printed article as it appeared in The New Statesman, April 12, 1913.
- Levy, J.H.
  See: Mrs. Warren's profession.
- London reform union leaflet.
  See: Metropolitan Borough Council Elections
- 11. Manifesto of English Socialists. Title page written on by Shaw in holograph. explaining how the manifesto came to be written. Approximately 15 lines in holograph., May 1st, 1893.; 8pp. wrappers. 8pp. printed pamphlet, original wrappers. (Box 2)
  This wretched affair was the result of a conference at William Morris's house at Hammersmith, lasting through several evenings, at which he attempted the hopeless task of reconciling Hyndman's policy with mine... etc.
- 12. Metropolitan Borough Council elections. Polling Day, Monday, November 2nd, 8am to 8pm., 1903. (Box 2)
  Progress, not politics. A word to women electors about the Boroough Councils. 4pp. Progressive leaflet no.7.
  Ten reasons why women should support the progressives at the Borough Council Elections Holograph manuscript by G.B. Shaw. 6pp.
  Galton, Frank Wallis: The London reform. Union Leaflet.
  Mr. Shaw's skit thereon (Memorandum by F.W. Galton), July 20, 1931. 1p. typescript, signed.
- Muddle over the Irish grant.
  See: [Irish Co-operation].
- 14. Norman, Clarence Henry, defendant. (Box 2)
  Proceedings of a District Court Martial held on the 30th day of June 1916 by order of Major General Sir F. Lloyd, K.C.B., G.V.O, D.S.O.,... Trial of no.25801 Private Clarence Henry Norman, 5th (R) Bn. Grenadier Guards... 34 leaves, printed and typed. (together) with holograph letter from G.B.S to My dear Norman regarding trial, dated August 19th, 1916 and letter of December 1934 from Offices of Simon & Schuster, publishers, New York. re K. McKenna re possible publication of this item.
- 15. Plays, pleasant and unpleasant [Prospectus]., Typescript with holograph corrections, 4pp. (Box 2)
  At top of sheet 9 Henrietta St., Covent Garden, London, W.C.
- Sobeniowski, Floryan
  See: Caesar and Cleopatra.
  See: Intelligent Woman's guide to socialism and capitalism.
- Stieglitz, Alfred
  See: Camera work.
- Ten reasons why women should support... (Box 2)
  See: Metropolitan Borough council elections.
- To the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor of Dublin..., November 28th, 1912.; 17; Galley proof, 1p. (Box 2)
  A letter concerning the providing of a suitable gallery for the Sir Hugh Lane Collection of Works of art.
  Not recorded in the bibliography of Shaw. Only a few copies were taken for the purpose of circulating others interested in the matter.
- 18. Tolstoy: Tragedian or Comedian. Published: London Mercury. Copyright: International Magazine Company, New York., 1921.; Galley proofs with holograph corrections. 2pp. (Box 2)
- 19. War issues for Irishmen. London., 1918.; 1 signature only, rough proof copy. (Box 2)
- 21. Letters, post-cards and autographed ephemera., 1901-.; 15 pieces, 1 folder. (Box 2)
  Letters to P.P. Howe, 1911; Leigh Lovel, 1915; Willard Houghland, 1934. Form-cards re forthcoming publications, cancelled check etc.
- Ephemera in printed form., n.d., 1942.; 22; 9 pieces, 1 folder. (Box 2)
  Contains such pieces as Bernard Shaw on capital punishment, Dreiser's statement to the Writers' War Board, 1942 concerning his position on war and capitalism, and Shaw on Dreiser, reprinted from PM, 1942. Playbill of Royal Court Theatre, April 9, 1904 for performance of Candida, A note to Androcles and the Lion for the New York production, 1915 etc.
  1 piece gift of Dr. Jacob Schwartz.
- 23. Clippings., v.d.; 1 folder. (Box 2)
- 24. Portraits, photos., 11 pieces, 1 folder. (Box 2)
  Photo of J. Epstein's bust of Shaw, 2 photos of L. Knight's oil portrait, clipped caricature of Shaw and Ellen Terry by W. Cotton.
- 25. Material re Kenneth MacKenna's collecting activities., 1 folder, 13 items. (Box 2)
- 26. Bust, caricature of G.B. Shaw in wood., 25cm. (Box 3)
- 27. Wire caricature by Ted Weidhaas., 22cm. (Box 3)
- Beardsley, Aubrey Vincent, 1872-1898. Poster for Arms and the Man., 28; Black and white. 50 × 70 cm.
  Stored in map-room with oversized catalogued material.
- Shaw, George Bernard. Spoken English & broken English. London: Linguaphone Institute., [1928?].; 29; 12pp., wrappers. (Box 2)
- 30. Shaw, George Bernard. Pamphlets., (7 items). (Box 2)
  - 1. Socialism for millionaires. Girard, Kansas: Haldeman-Julius., n.d. (Box 2)
  - 2. Epigrams. Girard, Kansas: Haldeman-Julius., n.d. (Box 2)
  - 3. The unprotected child and the law. London: The Six Point Group. (Box 2)
  - 4. The League of Nations. London: Fabian Society., January 1929.; 2 copies. (Box 2)
  - 5. Socialism and superior brains: a reply to Mr. Mallock. London: Fabian Society., November 1909. (Box 2)
  - 6. Troubetskoy, Prince Paul. Sculpture. With a word by Bernard Shaw. London: P. & D. Colnaghi & Company., December 1931. (Box 2)
  - 7. Lloyd, Henry J. Trade unionism for clerks., [1919]. (Box 2)
    By... and R.E. Scouller. With introductions by The Rt. Hon. J.R. Clynes and G. Bernard Shaw. London: Cecil Palmer and Hayward.
- 31. Henderson, Archibald. George Bernard Shaw. Man of the century. Washington: Reference Department, Library of Congress., 1957. (Box 2)
- Shaw, George Bernard, 1856-1950. Letters to Howard Von Hardenburg Inches. Ayot Saint Lawrence., 1947-1949.; 32; 6 items. Holograph and typescript. These letters have all been laminated. (Box 2)
  Accompanying the letter of January 8, 1948, is a signed photograph of Shaw.
  Also: 1 letter to Inches from Shaw's housekeeper, December 1, 1948.
  Gift of Howard V.H. Inches, June 1962.